All right, בוקר טוב, boker tov, חודש טוב. chodesh tov. We begin
top of ט עמוד א, tet amud aleph, דף ט. daf tet.
New משנה, mishna, we get back, we had a whole interesting little
digression about בכור, bechor, but now we get back to straight תמורה
temurah discussions. Let's take a look. ממירים מן הצאן על הבקר מן
הבקר על הצאן. Memirin min hatzon al habakar, min habakar al hatzon.
You can do תמורה. temurah. Need I remind you that the ability
to do תמורה temurah is not a good thing, but okay, it
is effective and you do an act of תמורה temurah when you
go from... well that's true, when you go from sheep to cattle
or cattle to sheep. It doesn't have to be the same type
of animal, right? If you have a sheep that's an עולה, olah,
you can do תמורה, temurah, you can try to exchange it with
a cow, even if it's not even if it's not the same
type and even if it's not even appropriate for that קדושה. kedusha.
Not from let's say if it's an עוף of to עוף of
you can't do a בקר bakar for that, right?
We'll see about that. מן הכבשים על העזים מן העזים על הכבשים.
Min hakvasim al haizim, min haizim al hakvasim. So you're right, עוף
of is not mentioned in this משנה. mishna. From sheep to goats
and goats to sheep, which should be pretty obvious if you can
go from sheep to cows or from whatever, flock to cows. מן
הזכרים על הנקבות ומן הנקבות על הזכרים. Min hazcharim al hanekeivos, umin
hanekeivos al hazcharim. From males to females, females to males. Even if
again the type of sanctity that you have given the animal, let's
say it's an עולה, olah, does not work for females, the תמורה
temurah is effective. We will see later what happens. Now I have
a female that's sanctified with a קדושה kedusha of an עולה, olah,
or I have a cow that's sanctified as a חטאת. chatas. You
know, what exactly what exactly do you do with that? How do
you you know so we will talk about that later. מן התמימים
על בעלי מומים. Min hatmimim al baalei mumim.
From unblemished to blemished animals. This is a case where even if
an animal starts with a מום, mum, normally if an animal starts
with a מום mum and I try to sanctify it, it cannot
get קדושת קרבן kedushas korban because you know it starts with a
מום, mum, it's like I tried to sanctify my car. But if
I do תמורה, temurah, because the תורה Torah says והיה הוא ותמורתו
יהיה קדש, vehaya hu utemurato yihye kodesh, the קדושה kedusha that resided
in the original animal now resides in the second one even if
the second one started with a מום. mum. I can't bring the
second as a קרבן, korban, it has a מום, mum, but it
has a but it has a full קדושת קרבן kedushas korban with
a מום. mum. Okay, so that's from unblemished to blemished. מן בעלי
מומים על התמימים. Min baalei mumim al hatmimim. From and from blemished
to unblemished, which is even more obvious, although that's something you might
have thought, oh that's a good thing, I'm exchanging a blemished with
an unblemished. But no but so not only does it take effect,
but it's still an act of תמורה. temurah. I want to get
back to that in a minute. Let's finish the משנה. mishna. שנאמר
Shene'emar is the verse says לא יחליפנו ולא ימיר אתו טוב ברע
או רע בטוב. lo yachalifenu velo yamir oto tov bera o ra
betov.
You should not exchange it and you should not transfer it, however
ימיר yamir is pretty similar to יחליפנו. yachalifenu. We'll talk about that
in the גמרא. Gemara. Good for bad or bad for good. ואיזהו
טוב ברע? Ve'eizu hu tov bera? What is an example of a
good one in exchange for a bad one? So or it's a
question here whether whether
when it says טוב ברע, tov bera, which is the sanctified one,
which is the one you're starting with and which is the second
one. רש"י Rashi says that the the the first word in the
פסוק pasuk is the is the non-sanctified animal. You're trying to exchange
a good animal for a bad one. Okay, so טוב ברע tov
bera meaning your קדושה kedusha starts in the bad animal and you're
now trying to put a good one in its place. תוספות Tosafos
says the opposite, we'll work with רש"י. Rashi. So what is that
a טוב ברע? tov bera? But here you'll see why the משנה
mishna is hard that way. בעלי מומים שקודם הקדשם נעשו מומים. Baalei
mumim shekodem hekdesham naasu mumim. It's only when we say that you
can do תמורה temurah on a בעל מום, baal mum, excuse me,
that you can do תמורה temurah from a בעל מום, baal mum,
if the animal's קדושה kedusha starts with a בעל מום, baal mum,
is an animal that starts that was sanctified and then got a
מום. mum. But if the animal because you'll remember that if I
first sanctify it and then it gets a מום, mum, not in
the תמורה temurah case, normally, then it has full קדושה kedusha of
a קרבן, korban, it just has a מום. mum. But if it
starts with a מום mum and I sanctify it, if it starts
with a מום, mum, then like I said, then it's like a
couch, then it's like a car, then it's not even a proper
object and the sanctity was never קדושת קרבן. kedushas korban. בדק הבית.
Bedek habayis. בדק הבית. Bedek habayis.
But there's no but
there's no תמורה temurah by בדק הבית. Bedek habayis. תמורה temurah is
only by קרבנות. korbanos. Okay, the whole concept of תמורה temurah is
only by קרבנות. korbanos. So therefore, when it says that תמורה temurah
applies like if the animal that I start with has a מום,
mum, it only is a case where the קדושה kedusha was first
given to that animal and then it got a מום. mum. Now
because it has קדושת קרבן, kedushas korban, it started with that קדושה
kedusha and it retains it, now I can do תמורה. temurah. But
if the animal started with a מום mum and I sanctified it,
now it's then now I can't do תמורה. temurah. If I tried
or whatever, it's not תמורה temurah because fundamentally it's not קדושת קרבן.
kedushas korban. So what happens? You've said nothing. Yeah, it doesn't take
effect and it doesn't whether it works as a it's an interesting
question. I have to think about that. Would it work as a
type of פדיון pidyon if it's not working as a תמורה? temurah?
Would it be effective essentially the way you want it to be
effective?
I mean what say you let's say I did sanctify my car
for קדושת בדק הבית kedushas bedek habayis and then I took another
car and I said זה תחת זה. zeh tachas zeh. That's an
interesting question. I'll use that question to bring on the second point
I wanted to say. I don't know yet the answer to that
but I will tell you the second point I wanted to say,
which is so now I've got this animal that has a מום.
Mum. And now I've been told that I can do the transgression
of תמורה, Tmurah, right? I sanctified it first and it's for קדושת
קרבן, Kdushas Korban, now it's got a מום. Mum. Now if I
took another perfect beautiful animal which I should you know and I
said זה תחת זה, Zeh Tachas Zeh, I've now transgressed תמורה. Tmurah.
But the point is what the heck am I supposed to do?
This animal has a מום. Mum. Aren't I supposed to redeem its
value and then go ahead and use those proceeds to buy another
קרבן Korban without a blemish to bring a קרבן, Korban, right? I
sanctified this as an עולה. Olah. It's got a מום. Mum. What's
the הלכה Halacha if I have a קרבן Korban with a with
a מום? Mum? You you redeem it, you use that money, you
buy another קרבן, Korban, and now you bring the other the other
thing as a קרבן. Korban. So so if I took money and
I said I am redeeming this onto this money and then I
took this money and I bought another קרבן Korban or I transferred
the קדושה Kdusha to another animal, that would be perfect.
Is there a way I can take an unblemished animal and effectively
do the same thing? Say I am redeeming this animal with a
blemish on this unblemished animal? Or is it that every time I
use another animal and I do it directly, that's seen as a
תמורה Tmurah and the prohibition?
Does it depend on what you say? So what if I actually
really said I'm פודה? Podeh?
Ah, so that is so so basically a number of ראשונים Rishonim
say, the שיטה מקובצת, Shita Mekubetzes, המנחת חינוך Haminchas Chinuch says this
in passing, he says you can do it directly to another animal
because this one has a blemish, it's supposed to be redeemed, and
it matters what you say. The שיטה מקובצת Shita Mekubetzes actually says
it matters what you do. What does that mean? So the מנחת
חינוך Minchas Chinuch says the following: if I say I am exchanging,
you know, A for B, that's תמורה, Tmurah, you've violated the both
codes, you get מלקות. Malkus. If I said I am redeeming this
one with the blemish and taking that קדושה, Kdusha, I'm redeeming it
and putting it on B, on the other one, then it's מותר
Mutar and that's what I am supposed to do. So it sounds
pretty much the same, exchanging versus redeeming, except conceptually the difference seems
to be that if I say I'm redeeming, I'm starting with the
one that's got a problem and I am taking away its קדושה
Kdusha and I am putting it on something else. So the place
of the origin is the one with the problem, the one with
the קדושה Kdusha that has a מום. Mum. If I say I'm
exchanging, the focus is a little different. The focus is I like
this one better, let's use this one instead. And therefore that is
some of some affront, you know, to the one that I've already
got. It doesn't say this has a problem, I have to remove
it. No, this is better, this will take the place. So that's
the that could just be a simple question of the words you
use. The שיטה מקובצת Shita Mekubetzes says essentially the same thing but
there's even a physical act. He says where are you placing your
hands? Not like you have to place your hands, but he says
if you place your hands on the new one, the unblemished one,
and you say זה תחת זה, Zeh Tachas Zeh, this one will
be the replacement, that's תמורה. Tmurah. If you place your hands on
the one that has the קדושה Kdusha but has the blemish and
you say, he says even if you say זה תחת זה, Zeh
Tachas Zeh, same words, but you start with the one with the
blemish and place your hands on it and you say I'm going
to have something else take this place, that's actually a פדיון Pidyon
not a תמורה, Tmurah, which is funny because you're using the exact
same words. But they both agree that the concept is if you
basically focus on the new one and say I want it to
take the I want this instead, that's תמורה. Tmurah. If you focus
on the old one and you say I'm removing the קדושה, Kdusha,
I'm redeeming it, then that's actually what you're supposed to do. So
the idea of תמורה Tmurah with an animal that has a blemish,
that the קדושה Kdusha one has a blemish, is a funny idea
because you are supposed to remove the קדושה Kdusha and you're supposed
to redeem it, you're just not supposed to do it through the
process of תמורה. Tmurah. You had a question?
So in other words, תמורה Tmurah is when someone who intends to
give a sacrifice should be more diligent in in choosing the animal
and his verbal his formal statement?
Right, I mean, it's I mean, he might it might not have
been a question of diligence. He might have picked a perfect animal
but then it got a blemish afterwards. Oh, I see.
So so this thing is the leeway of a human error with
intention I guess?
Yeah,
this isn't a question of diligence. It's a question of, you know,
how you're framing when you now come to exchange it. That's I
mean, you have to be diligent in what you say, but what
you say can profoundly redefine the act that you're doing.
Okay, let me just make sure I understand this. So, you know,
like let's say it wasn't a a מום. Mum. It was a
perfectly good animal and he just wants to redeem it.
Yeah, then it wouldn't matter.
Maybe because I'm trying to redeem this one no matter what he
did, that's not a Presumably correct.
Presumably if it has and does not have a blemish, then that's
a good question, but based on what I just said, but presumably
if it does not have a blemish, since redemption is not a
relevant concept at this stage because it's unblemished, any attempt to transfer
whatever is considered תמורה. Tmurah. But with a blemish where redemption is
a legitimate and appropriate move, then if you define it as redeeming
you're okay, if you define it as תמורה Tmurah Oh, so wait,
so
if he's trying to redeem it then that's actually considered תמורה Tmurah
as opposed to him having said nothing?
I would think so. I mean, again, this is not always fully
spelled out and I have to see if I can find more
explicit discussion. But that is my understanding. If it doesn't have a
blemish and you say, it's a perfect animal with קדושה, kedushah, and
you say I'm redeeming this for this, even if you use the
word redeeming, essentially, and actually we're going to see a case even
at the end of this גמרא Gemara that's even more extreme than
that, but essentially since you're trying to transfer the קדושה kedushah from
an unblemished animal, that's תמורה. tmurah. I think the only distinction of
how you frame it as תמורה tmurah versus פדיון pidyon is when
it has a blemish and פדיון pidyon is relevant. Okay, but again,
these things are not fully fleshed out. Let's take a look at
the גמרא. Gemara. Okay,
מנא הני מילי? Mena hani mili? Where is this from? That, meaning
that this, it doesn't matter what type of animal you're doing, etc.,
but there is one issue about when it got the blemish. דתנו
רבנן, Detanu rabanan, we taught: בהמה בבהמה. Behemah b'behemah. It says, לא
יחליפנו ולא
ימיר אותו טוב ברע או רע בטוב ואם המר ימיר
בהמה בבהמה והיה הוא ותמורתו יהיה קודש. Lo yachlifenu v'lo yamir oto
tov b'ra o ra b'tov v'im hamer yamir behemah b'behemah v'hayah hu
u'tmurato yihiyeh kodesh. If you exchange one בהמה behemah for another. So
בהמה behemah is very generic. So מכאן שמימר מן הצאן על הבקר
מן הבקר על הצאן. Mikan she'meimir min hatzon al habakar min habakar
al hatzon. All of these fit the definition of בהמה בבהמה. behemah
b'behemah. Sheep on cattle, cattle on sheep. מן הכבשים על העזים ומן
העזים על הכבשים. Min hakevasim al ha'izim u'min ha'izim al hakevasim. Goats
on sheep, sheep on goats. מן הזכרים על הנקבות ומן הנקבות על
הזכרים. Min hazcharim al hanekeivot u'min hanekeivot al hazcharim. Male on female,
female on male. They're all בהמה בבהמה. behemah b'behemah. מן בעלי מומין
על תמימים ומן תמימים על בעלי מומין. Min ba'alei mumin al temimim
u'min temimim al ba'alei mumin. Blemished to unblemished, unblemished to blemished. Now,
everything is בהמה בבהמה, behemah b'behemah, very generic. Now, יכול אפילו קדם
מום להקדשן? Yachol afilu kadam mum lehekdeshan? Maybe it's even a transgression
of תמורה tmurah if the blemish was on the animal before I
sanctified it? And remember, that means that the sanctity of the animal
was never קרבן korban sanctity, was never קדושת הגוף. kedushat haguf. Maybe
even that is included? תלמוד לומר: Talmud lomar: לא יחליפנו ולא ימיר
אותו טוב ברע או רע בטוב. Lo yachlifenu v'lo yamir oto tov
b'ra o ra b'tov. Don't exchange good for bad, bad for good.
איזהו טוב ברע? Eizehu tov b'ra? What's good for bad? בעלי מומין
שקדם הקדשן את מומן. Ba'alei mumin shekadam hekdeshan et muman. Only if
the sanctity
preceded the blemish. Okay, so מה תלמוד לומר? Mah talmud lomar? Where
are you getting that from the פסוק? pasuk? It's very nice, we
understand why you want to exclude that case, but where are you
getting it from the language of טוב ורע ורע בטוב? tov v'ra
v'ra b'tov? So אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, Abaye says: נימא קרא לא
יחליפנו ולא ימיר אותו טוב ברע או רע בו. Neima kra lo
yachlifenu v'lo yamir oto tov b'ra o ra bo. It didn't have
to say the second טוב. tov. It could have said, don't exchange
good for bad or bad for it. Now, so since it already
said good, the implication would have been or bad for good. So
why did it say טוב tov again? בטוב אחרינא למה לי? B'tov
achrina lamah li? Why did it say with a good one a
second time? That could have been implicit. שמע מינה, Shma minah, to
tell you that the animal that it is, that you are, that
it's originating in, the one with the קדושה, kedushah, has to have
an element of טוב. tov. What does that mean? טוב מעיקרא עושה
תמורה רע מעיקרא אין עושה תמורה. Tov me'ikara oseh tmurah ra me'ikara
ein oseh tmurah.
It had to at least have been good at the outset. It
had to have an element of טוב tov in it. But if
it was bad from the outset, if it started with a blemish,
then it never had a, it was never an aspect of טוב.
tov. Because חז"ל Chazal understand bad for good, good for bad, not
like what we'd think, like high quality, low quality. They understand it
meaning in a very technical קרבן korban sense, blemished and unblemished. Or
at least that's one possible meaning of it. So the fact that
the תורה Torah that here the word בטוב b'tov is seen as
somewhat redundant is coming to tell me that the animal you start
with always has to have an element of טוב, tov, which means
that when it was sanctified it had to be unblemished. But if
when it was sanctified it was blemished, it was רע ra in
that sense, then it is not relevant for תמורה tmurah because the
קדושה kedushah it had was never a קדושת הגוף kedushat haguf for
קרבן. korban.
You mean the whole thing is redundant? If I know that I
can't substitute
if it started out bad, I can't do a good one, I
certainly if it started out good I can't do a bad.
So the גמרא's Gemara going to, so the גמרא Gemara will get
to that a little bit right now. So let's take a look.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this: אמר רבא, Amar Rava,
Rava says: תרווייהו טוב יתירא מיעסרי. Travaihu tov yateira mi'asrei.
Both of the טובs tov are a little extra. אם כן נכתוב
קרא לא יחליפנו ולא ימיר טוב ברע או רע בו. Im ken
nichtov kra lo yachlifenu v'lo yamir tov b'ra o ra bo.
Just say don't exchange it for a bad one or a bad
one for it. And by implication, the other thing we're talking about
is good, since you're calling this thing bad. Okay, so למה לי
למכתב תרווייהו טוב? Lamah li limichtav travaihu tov?
Why are both טובs tov needed? חד טוב Chad tov is even,
now again, the text is a little problematic here, it's clear later
that the text is אפילו טוב בטוב. afilu tov b'tov.
Even a good one with a good one you can't exchange. That's
what the extra word good is. Now of course Michael says, כל
שכן, kol sheken, if you can't exchange a bad one for a
good one, you can't exchange a good one for a good one.
So we're going to get to that in a minute, but that's
not explicit in the פסוק. pasuk. So one extra טוב tov is
coming to say you can't even do good for good. You can
understand how that a little bit fell out of the text. It's
a little
טוב אפילו טוב בטוב. tov afilu tov b'tov. Okay, like four טובs
tov in three words. Anyway, נמי כי מימר לקי, Nami ki meimar
laki, to tell you that even good for good, that you get
lashes, that's an extra טוב tov is to tell you that. ואידך,
V'idach, and the other, so one extra טוב tov to tell you
that, what does the extra טוב tov tell you? טוב מעיקרא עושה
תמורה רע מעיקרא אינו עושה תמורה. Tov me'ikara oseh tmurah ra me'ikara
eino oseh tmurah.
It's only a תמורה tmurah if it started with an element of
טוב. tov. If it started unblemished and you sanctified it. And then
it got the blemish. But if it started with a blemish and
you sanctified it, it never had קדושת הגוף kedushat haguf for קרבן
korban and it's not relevant for the world of תמורה. tmurah. Okay,
so now we're going to see רבא's Rava need to also explicitly
relate to a case of good with good. Okay, so let's take
a look. אביי Abaye is going to ask essentially what Michael was
asking. Let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says like this:
ואביי אמר, ve'Abaye amar,
אביי Abaye will say,
to רבא Rava you mean?
To רבא. Rava. To רבא. Rava. קל וחומר, kal vachomer,
what do you mean you need a פסוק pasuk for good for
good? קל וחומר הוא. kal vachomer hu. ומה טוב ברע, uma tov
bera, when you're trying to exchange a good one for a bad
one, דעילויי קא מעלי ליה, de'iluyei ka ma'alei lei, that you're trying
to improve the status, לקי, laki, you still get lashes. טוב בטוב,
tov betov,
דכי הדדי נינהו, dechi hadadi ninhu, good for good where you're basically,
you know, doing the same thing, לא כל שכן דלקי, lo kol
sheken delaki, certainly you'd get lashes. You're not even trying to make
it any better. ורבא, veRava, רבא Rava would say back to you,
אין עונשין מן הדין. ein onshin min hadin. It's true, it is
a קל וחומר, kal vachomer, but if it's not explicit, you don't
get lashes for something that you learn out from a קל וחומר.
kal vachomer. Okay, and therefore you need it to be explicit. Of
course then the question is how do you know about רע ברע?
ra bera? But presumably רע ברע ra bera is also is טוב
בטוב. tov betov. I mean it's the same, they're the same level.
Anyway, ואביי, ve'Abaye, אביי Abaye would say to you, אמר לך, amar
lach, הא לאו דינא הוא. ha lav dina hu.
This isn't a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. מי גרע טוב מרע? mi
gara tov mera?
It's not any worse than good than exchanging a good one for
a bad one. Meaning, it's always an interesting question, right? What's a
קל וחומר? kal vachomer? Is a קל, kal, like if I say
you owe me $200 and קל וחומר kal vachomer you owe me
$100, right?
Or you know, is that a קל וחומר kal vachomer or is
that just implicit in the first statement? So, so that seems to
be right what אביי, Abaye, you know,
or if a six-foot person is taller than a five-foot person, קל
וחומר kal vachomer a seven-foot person is taller. Is that a קל
וחומר kal vachomer or is that just like, you know, is that
just included in the first point that anybody six feet and higher
is taller than a five-foot person? So that seems to be what
אביי Abaye is saying, right? אביי Abaye is saying, or I'll give
you another example which really bears it out. The גמרא Gemara needs
a פסוק pasuk to understand that a sister,
a half-sister from the father or a half-sister from the mother is
one of the עריות. arayot. And then it says how do you
know full sister? And it learns it out from a פסוק. pasuk.
Why? Why do you learn it out from a קל וחומר? kal
vachomer? אין עונשין מן הדין. ein onshin min hadin. So we would
normally say who needs a קל וחומר? kal vachomer? A full sister
is a half-sister plus. She's my sister on my father's side and
she's my sister on my mother's side. So at what stage do
you say this is a different thing?
It's obviously, it's logically implicit. It's logically, you know, you obviously know
it logically, but fundamentally it's a different thing. Or you say it's
the same thing plus. And that seems to be what אביי Abaye
is saying back to רבא, Rava, right? רבא Rava is saying, oh,
good for good is a different thing. Of course it's a קל
וחומר, kal vachomer, but it's a different thing. And אביי Abaye is
saying no, no, no. The whole point is that if you say
that you can't exchange something good for something worse, what it means
is even, I'm sorry, something bad for something good, it means, let
me try that again. You can't exchange something bad for something good.
It means even if you're improving it. But included in that statement
is certainly if you're not improving it. It's not saying only concretely
bad for good. It's saying bad even if you want to do
good. But that already includes the idea of keeping things at the
same level. Okay, so that's the interesting question of when do you
call something something different that you is a קל וחומר kal vachomer
or something that's essentially included in the first statement. Okay, but they
do not address Michael's question, I would say, and I know he's
going to go back to it, which is fine. Okay, but why
do you have to say, what was it?
Oh, once you say that, the question is to אביי. Abaye. רבא
Rava that says everything needs a קל וחומר, kal vachomer, fine, you
need to say everything separately. But according to אביי Abaye that says
it's all implicit, so once you said, once you said you can't
do bad for good, why do you need to say good for
bad, right? So that's a very good question. So basically the answer
seems to be to tell you that it has to be טוב
מעיקרא. tov me'ikara. To tell you that only when the original animal
was with the, you're right, we know that you can't do something
good for bad if the animal starts as good, it's קל וחומר
kal vachomer or implicit you can't do it for bad. But it
says good for bad to tell you טוב מעיקרא. tov me'ikara. That
we're only dealing with when the, when it began unblemished and then
got the מום, mum, right? Yeah.
But that's what אביי Abaye said in the beginning though. He could
have said that oh,
if we just did the,
no, he's right, it's
just the word טוב tov in the beginning. Yeah, I know, it's
a good point.
Yeah, I also would expect that you could, without the פסוק pasuk
you would have קל וחומר kal vachomer or whatever you want to
call it. But you know, one also suspects that the גמרא Gemara
could just as easily say גזירת הכתוב. gezeirat hakatuv. Only טוב ברע
tov bera but not רע ברע. ra bera.
Right,
and the גמרא Gemara does that sometimes too. How often does logic
dictate? Right? I don't know.
Possibly the answer to you, Michael, is, and we'll see that in
a minute in the גמרא, Gemara, is that you might have known
it's prohibited. What I would say like this, you could have said
bad for good is so inappropriate, I mean, try to replace a
good one with a bad one is so inappropriate, maybe it's not
even an act at all. Or maybe you want to say והיה
הוא ותמורתו יהיה קודש, vehaya hu utmurato yihye kodesh, which the גמרא
Gemara also says. Maybe I could
have
known... I might have thought so. If the second object is completely
inappropriate, it wouldn't extend the קדושה kedusha to it.
Somewhat like an oath then? What? Like if you did an oath?
Right, well we have, we'll see what that's going to be. All
right, so anyway it's a good question. Okay, but now we see
that all these things are prohibited. Good for bad, bad for good,
one who's thinking you have to start with קדושת קרבן, kedushas korban,
so if you sanctify the animal and it already had a מום,
mum, it's not תמורה. tmura. Now let's keep on going. תנו
רבנן. Tano rabbanan. לא יחליפנו בשל אחרים ולא ימירנו בו בשל עצמו.
Lo yachlifenu beshel acherim velo yamiru bo beshel atzmo. Don't exchange it
with somebody else and don't do a transfer on your own. So
exchange somebody
else's, I've got a קרבן korban which then Michael has an animal
and I say Michael let's swap, you take my animal I'll take
yours. Now what's exactly going to happen? Presumably you take my animal
that's sanctified and I'll take yours and when I take yours your
animal will now take the place of mine as the קרבן. korban.
So Michael will give me his sheep, that will now become my
קרבן, korban, the קדושה kedusha I want to transfer to that and
I give him my sheep which had קדושה kedusha and I give
it to him and it now becomes desanctified. So it's the same
idea but we're doing it with two people, maybe and that's לא
יחליפנו. lo yachlifenu. The idea of תחליף, tachlif, exchange, suggests a more
real-world type of an exchange. Okay, so then you do get מלקות.
malkus. I get מלקות malkus because I'm the one that has controls
the sanctity because it's my קרבן. korban. Okay, the other scenario would
be you know just I start with the non-sanctified, Michael starts with
the sanctified. But that's really the same same scenario just just you
start from Michael's end rather than mine. Okay, one person has it,
has sanctified, the other has unsanctified, they're trying to swap and get
the sanctity to swap with it. Okay, that's לא יחליפנו. lo yachlifenu.
And וזהו תמורתו v'zehu tmurato means even on לא יחליפנו lo yachlifenu
it both becomes קודש. kodesh.
Right,
and that's going to be the גמרא's Gemara question. How do I
have the ability to make your animal קודש? kodesh? So we'll talk
about that. Okay, anyway but let's say so we'll get to לא
יחליפנו. lo yachlifenu. ולא ימירנו בו בשל עצמו. Velo yamiru bo beshel
atzmo. And if they're both mine I also can't just say A
for B. Fine. So now the גמרא Gemara says, so in the
case of exchange with somebody else it's a little bit of a
question of how do I have the right to define what happens
to somebody else's? We'll talk about that. But anyway both of them
I'm basically trying to exchange. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says
ולכתוב לא יחליפנו ולא בעי לא ימירנו בו. velichtov lo yachlifenu velo
ba'i lo yamiru bo. Let's just say לא יחליפנו lo yachlifenu and
it would be obvious of לא ימירנו בו. lo yamiru bo. Now
why is it obvious that that's also prohibited? So in one explanation
the שיטה מקובצת Shita Mekubetzet says it's not that one is more
obvious than the other. Basically means they're both essentially the same case.
Why do I need two cases? They're both I'm just trying to
transfer the קדושה kedusha from one to another. Another possibility though is
that לא ימיר lo yamir is more obvious that since they're both
mine it's more obvious that I control the situation. So therefore לא
יחליפנו lo yachlifenu you might have said good luck, you know it's
not your animal to begin with, whatever, the act isn't so meaningful.
And even if that's prohibited certainly when I control the situation and
can totally designate how much more so is it a meaningful act
and is it prohibited. Okay, but either way the גמרא Gemara says
that you do not need to have said both. Why couldn't it
have just said לא יחליפנו? lo yachlifenu? Says גמרא Gemara says like
this, אי כתיב הכי, i ksiv hachi, if it had just said
לא יחליפנו, lo yachlifenu, הוה אמינא תצא זו ותיכנס זו הוא דתילקי.
hava amina tetzei zu vesikaneis zu hu detilki. When I say one
goes out and the other comes in, it's a real exchange, לא
יחליפנו, lo yachlifenu, that's when I get lashes.
אבל מימר, Aval meimer, by תוסיף תמורה teseif tmura which they're both
mine, דתרוייהו קמקדש, detarvaihu kamakdish, that both of them are sanctified. ליה,
Lahu, I'm sanctifying both, אימא לא לילקי, eima lo larki, I would
say you don't get
lashes, קא משמע לן. kamashma lan. Now what the heck does that
mean? So it sounds like it's saying that in the case where
they're both mine I'm not trying to exchange it. I'm just trying
to say I have one animal that's my קרבן korban and I
say let the second one also have the קדושה kedusha the first
one. I'm trying to extend it, not to exchange it. And even
so I get lashes. Okay, and actually that is what some ראשונים
Rishonim understand from this גמרא. Gemara. שיטה מקובצת, Shita Mekubetzet, רש"י, Rashi,
it sounds like they're basically saying that yeah if they're both my
animals and this is shocking because the whole idea of תמורה tmura
was an attempt to replace. And now it seems based on this
little innocent line in the גמרא Gemara that no, even if I
just try to extend the קדושה kedusha that's also considered תמורה. tmura.
You mean to say that this will be קודש kodesh and also
like that?
I say yeah this is קדוש, kadosh, I take this other animal
and I say let the קדושה kedusha from this extend to this,
also apply to that. Not remove but also.
So that's considered תמורה. tmura.
Right, which is completely bizarre. Where have we ever heard such a
thing? Okay, so רבינו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom has a slightly different line.
And the way he phrases the גמרא Gemara is not that you're
sanctifying both but you have the ability to sanctify both. And what
רבינו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom says is the following is that I might
have thought that in the case here and that I think is
along the lines that I was telling you before that I might
have thought that when when I both animals I own both. And
in principle I could sanctify both. The act of it fundamentally more
makes more sense that I since I could sanctify this, I was
the one that originally sanctified the first one, maybe in that case
you know I have I do have even the real power to
transfer it. and maybe therefore I don't get lashes. Okay, maybe what
I'm doing is not so absurd, or I'm therefore קא משמע לן
ka mashma lan that even in that case where I have the
power to sanctify both, I still get lashes. But the act I'm
trying to do is fundamentally an act of exchange. So I much
more prefer Rabbeinu Gershom's ריש. reish.
So how does he have the same text?
Well, I'll just read you what his text says. He says,
אבל מימר בשל עצמו aval meimar beshel atzmo it's four lines from
the bottom, דצבויי מצי מקדיש להו אימא לא לוקי. detzavuyei matzi makdish
lehu eima lo luki. I would say maybe you don't get lashes,
אלא ליקדשו לתרוייהו, ela likdeshu letravaihu, let both of them be sanctified.
Meaning, since I have the power to sanctify both, right, maybe what
we should do is we should say, okay, you said exchange, but
we'll translate what you said as let them both be sanctified. Since
anyway they're both mine, if I wanted to I could sanctify the
second one, we'll give you, you know, we'll interpret it more generously.
And although you said let me substitute A for B, maybe we'll
just say what you really mean is you wanted to sanctify B.
And maybe we'll get you off the hook. קא משמע לן ka
mashma lan no, you still tried to do an exchange. So according
to him, the word is מצי. matzi. What? He has the words
מצי מקדיש להו, matzi makdish lehu, not that you are being מקדיש
makdish them. Okay? דתרוייהו detravaihu not דקא מקדיש להו, deka makdish lehu,
but מצי מקדיש להו. matzi makdish lehu. So I much prefer that,
because according to others you come up with an idea we've never
heard elsewhere, which is that they're both my animals, even if I
just try to extend the קדושה, kedusha, it's תמורה. temurah. He says
no, no, no, it's only a הוה אמינא hava amina that because
you have the ability to מקדיש makdish them, maybe somehow it's a
qualitatively different act. As opposed to, or we'll interpret, right, as opposed
to somebody else's you don't fundamentally have the ability, we'll interpret the
act differently, it's a different type of an act. קא משמע לן
ka mashma lan it doesn't matter. Okay, so I totally, his explanation
really is the, for me, the only one that really makes sense.
Let's go on. So the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, האי
בשל אחרים היכי דמי? hai beshel acherim heichi dami? What's the case
of exchanging with somebody else?
אי נימא בהמה דהקדש דידי וחולין דעלמא, ei neima behema dehekdesh didi
vechullin dealma, it's my קרבן korban and it's Michael's unsanctified sheep. Okay,
so now מי מצי מקדיש? mi matzi makdish? And this really reinforces
Rabbeinu Gershom, right? It says here when it deals with somebody else,
the emphasis is how do I have the ability to sanctify somebody
else? The word מצי מקדיש. mi matzi makdish. So as a contrast
to my own where I have the ability. So the problem here
is how do, where's my ability to do this? So מי מצי
מקדיש? mi matzi makdish? איש כי יקדיש את ביתו קודש לה' אמר
רחמנא. ish ki yakdish et beito kodesh l'Hashem amar rachmana. If you
sanctify your house to God, מה ביתו ברשותו אף כל ברשותו. ma
beito birshuto af kol birshuto. It has to be yours and in
your control. So how if I'm exchanging with Michael do I think
I can sanctify Michael's sheep?
Okay,
now, ואלא בהמה דהקדש דעלמא וחולין דידי. ve'ela behema dehekdesh dealma vechullin
didi. Fine, Michael is the one providing the קודש kodesh sheep and
I'm providing the חולין chullin sheep. And what I basically say is,
fine, I'll give you my sheep, my חולין chullin sheep, it will
become your קרבן. korban. So since it's my sheep I can designate
it as Michael's קרבן. korban. And you give me your sheep and
the קדושה kedusha gets removed. But if that's true, מי מתפיס בדבר
שאינו שלו? mi matpis bedavar she'eino shelo? I'm not really sanctifying my
sheep. What I'm trying to do is I'm trying to take the
קדושה kedusha from Michael's קרבן korban and pull it onto my sheep.
That's the word מתפיס. matpis. You have to learn this word, it's
a technical word. מתפיס matpis is different than מקדיש. makdish. מקדיש makdish
is when I directly sanctify. מתפיס matpis from תופס tofes grab, is
when I try to transfer, make something קדוש kadosh by extending the
קדושה kedusha or transferring the קדושה kedusha from a pre-existing object, from
a pre-existing קדושה. kedusha. Okay? So the point is that I'm like
grabbing it on, I'm putting it in the clutches of the other
one. So the גמרא Gemara says, look, make up your mind. If
I'm giving Michael the קרבן korban and I'm getting his thing, so
I have the control over the קדושה kedusha of my קרבן, korban,
but I don't have the ability to extend it to
his sheep. If I'm the one giving my non-קרבן korban sheep to
Michael, I have the ability to have it apply to my sheep,
but I don't have the ability to grab the קדושה kedusha of
Michael's קרבן korban because it's his קרבן. korban. Right? So if I
don't, I need both. I need to be able to grab it
from one and I need the right to place it on the
other. Okay, and this is the problem with somebody else's. So the
גמרא Gemara says, לעולם מי מתפיס בדבר שאינו שלו? le'olam mi matpis
bedavar she'eino shelo? So it says לעולם בבהמה דהקדש דעלמא וחולין דידי.
le'olam bebehema dehekdesh dealma vechullin didi. It's Michael's קרבן, korban, it's my
sheep. Now how can I grab that קדושה kedusha and try to
put it on my sheep?
כגון
דאמר מרי דבהמה דהקדש,
kegon de'amar marei
debehema dehekdesh, because Michael, the master of this, the owner of this
קרבן korban says,
כל הרוצה להמיר בבהמתי יבא וימיר. kol harotze lehamir bebehemti yavo veyamir.
Whoever wants to use my animal for תמורה, temurah, it's open, you
can come and use it. So Michael here is being a מכשיל
את הרבים machshil et harabbim because he's making everybody behave as to
be עובר over on תמורה. temurah. But he stands up and he
makes this announcement: if you want to use my animal for תמורה,
temurah, go have a field day, it's all available. And therefore I'm
exchanging it with Michael and I can come and say I'm taking
the תמורה temurah off of your animal and I'm putting it on,
so I get the לוקה. loke. Now what? No, I get the
לוקה. loke. Now what? You do not. Now what is fascinating about
this is two points. First of all, you could have said why
is it such a problem if we're actually swapping animals, right, then
the fact that this animal of Michael's is coming into my control
makes it enough mine to give me the ability to transfer the
קדושה, kedusha, but maybe the גמרא Gemara still understands like make up
your mind, if it's in your control then the other one is
out of your control. And why you know so they're not both
in my control at the same time. So that's probably the גמרא's
Gemara's problem although you know again the very fact that it's a
swap might have made you think that the parameters change.
The other case for גניבה geneiva etc.
Like anyway the other thing that makes the גמרא Gemara fascinating is
as we're talking about בכור bechor and we're going to be talking
about later the whole ongoing question in this מסכת masechet is one
ongoing question is who is the owner of the בהמה behema that
has the right to do תמורה, temurah, right? So by בכור bechor
is the כהן kohen really the owner? The גמרא Gemara talks about
a case where I sanctify it for James there to bring it.
So I did the הפרשה hafrasha but he gets the he gets
the benefit he gets the you know the credit for the קרבן.
korban. He's considered the owner. So you would think that the הלכה
halacha is it's just the owner end of story. Now what we're
understanding once you'd identify who the owner is it's just the owner
who can do it. Now what it seems is no what we
identify the owner that says he's got the right or the privilege
the ability but it's but it's something that he can also allow
others to have as well but it's not a דין din that
תמורה temurah only applies to the בעל הקרבן. ba'al hakorban. The הלכה
halacha is that only the בעל הקרבן ba'al hakorban is in a
position to do that type of an act because he's in control.
But if he but if he relinquishes his control he permits others
to use to exercise that ability then others can also their act
of תמורה temurah is also meaningful. So that's a fascinating point here
that תמורה temurah is possibly not limited to the owner of the
קרבן korban if the owner allows other people to do that type
of an act.
Does he have to say it verbally?
Yeah he has to say it verbally. He has to let it
be known. I mean what if I know that James would allow
me but he hasn't explicitly allowed me? That's an interesting question because
you know a parallel to this is like תמורה temurah not תרומה
terumah תמורה. temurah. תרומה terumah is a parallel to this that the
גמרא Gemara says that I can't take תרומה terumah on James's grain.
But if James says כל הרוצה לתרום יבוא ויתרום kol harotze litrom
yavo veyitrom anybody who wants to take תרומה terumah from my grain
is able I'm giving permission then I can go and take תרומה
terumah on his grain. What if I know that he wants me
to without him having said it? So that also could work. So
maybe he doesn't even have to say it verbally if I know
it. But now we actually see that again it's not a הלכה
halacha that only the owners do תמורה. temurah. It's the owners have
the ability the power and but that is something that they can
allow others to partake of as well. Okay.
So in the previous section we said Michael just like made his
animal available for capture. Don't we have some kind of limit if
he's allowing a basically עבירה? aveira?
Right so that is it's like לפני עיוור lifnei iver or whatever
I understand.
But that's oh you mean
יבוא מהני? yavo mahani? From the previous גמרא Gemara even if you
do things that are violated it doesn't prevent them from taking effect.
Right and that was basically to some degree that was מחלוקת אביי
ורבא machloket Abaye veRava before. All right. So anyway but I just
want to say one final thing about this you do see that
the whole concern of the גמרא Gemara in the case of exchange
is how do I have that power? Why is that meaningful? How
do I have the power to be doing it anyway? Which now
really reinforces רבינו גרשום's Rabbeinu Gershom's read before that the contrast to
when they're both mine is not that I'm actually sanctifying both but
that I have the power to be doing what I'm doing. And
therefore I would have thought it's different but in this case how
do I even have the power to be doing this?
Right yeah I was just going to try to make that back
full circle. So the reason why I have to say לא יחליפנו
ולא ימיר אותו lo yachlifenu velo yamir oto is that because for
the there's two the source is just from different people right? So
I need and I couldn't have just said לא ימיר אותו lo
yamir oto because then you would have thought that oh because since
they're both in my control
maybe only then I get lashes because it's really meaningful because I
could I could really do what I'm doing.
And but if it was just לא יחליפנו lo yachlifenu then לא
ימיר אותו lo yamir oto right.
So then I would have said so you're saying it still goes
back to the question why is it a קל וחומר? kal vachomer?
If even in a case where I have weaker control certainly in
a case where I have more control. So it's not exactly clear
why the גמרא Gemara thought that the more control case I wouldn't
get lashes but maybe again what it sounds a little bit like
רבינו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom is well since I have so much control
maybe what I should be doing should be seen as legitimate or
more should be interpreted as legitimate as whereas the case of exchange
it's very blatantly an exchange. Okay. So that seems to be the
difference. Let's take a look now at the next משנה. mishnah. הממיר
אחד בשנים ושנים באחד. hamemir echad bishnayim ushnayim be'echad.
How about not just different types of animals but one for two
or two for one? Is that an act of תמורה? temurah? I
take one animal that's a קדוש kadosh and I say these two
sheep are in its stead. Or I take two sheep that are
קרבן korban and I say this one cow or this one sheep
is in its stead. Maybe you could say that since it's not
a real exchange and therefore it was a stupid thing but it
was not an act of תמורה. temurah. Okay. No you can do
it it is an act of תמורה. temurah. And not only that
and you get מלקות malkus right and the קדושה kedusha applies to
the other thing. Okay. אחד במאה מאה באחד echad beme'ah me'ah be'echad
even a hundred to one. רבי שמעון אומר אין ממיר אלא אחד
באחד. Rabbi Shimon omer ein memir ela echad be'echad. No only a
one to one exchange. שנאמר והיה הוא ותמורתו יהיה קודש. shene'emar vehaya
hu utmurato yihye kodesh.
It singular and its exchange all in the singular will be holy.
מה הוא מיוחד ma hu meyuchad the same way הוא hu is
singular אף היא או תמורתו מיוחדת af hi o tmurato meyuchadet
the exchange animal must be singular. is a singular one. One for
one only. One wonders according to רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*, two for
two, right? I don't know, do we translate that as two cases
of one-for-one? Anyway, let's take a look at the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*.
מנא הני מילי *Mina hani milei*? Where do you know this from?
תנו רבנן *Tanu rabanan*. בהמה behema, בבהמה *Behemah b'vehemah*, animal for animal,
which is what we focused on before about different types of animals.
מכאן שמתמורין אחד echad, בשנים ושנים באחד אחד במאה ומאה באחד *Mikan
shematmurin echad b'shnayim v'shnayim b'echad echad b'meah u'meah b'echad*. Even one for
two, two for one, we'll see in a minute, hundred for one,
one for hundred. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon, אומר *Rabbi Shimon omer*, אין
ממירין אלא אחד באחד *ein memirin ela echad b'echad*. שנאמר *shene'emar*, בהמה
בבהמה *behemah b'vehemah*, one for one, ולא בהמה בבהמה *v'lo behemah b'vehemah*,
not one for multiple. It says they're both in the singular. ולא
בהמות בבהמה *v'lo behemot b'vehemah*, not multiple for one. אמרו לו *Amru
lo*, they said back to him, no, we're going to explain to
you how we get it from the פסוק pasuk. *pasuk*. מצינו בהמות
שקרויה בהמה *Matzinu behemot shekruyah behemah*, multiple animals are called in the
singular. שנאמר *shene'emar*, ובהמה רבה *u'vehemah rabah*, right?
And and and a multitude of animals uses the word בהמה *behemah*.
All right, so what's the answer?
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Rabbi Shimon*, בהמה רבה איקרי *behemah rabah ikrei*,
a multitude of animals is called בהמה *behemah*. סתם *Stam*, the word
בהמה *behemah* by itself, לא איקרי *lo ikrei*, would not refer to
many animals, it refers to a singular animal. אבל צאן *Aval tzon*
though refers to multiple, but צאן *tzon* I guess means flock, right?
דכתיב ומה הצאן *Dechtiv u'mah hatzon*, right? You know, what is it
that שמואל
*Shmuel* says to שאול *Shaul*, ומה קול הצאן הזה *u'mah kol hatzon
hazeh*, whatever. Anyway, so okay, but it's got to be, it's got
to be צאן *tzon* or בהמה *behemah* means cattle in the generic,
doesn't it? Or animals in the generic?
ובהמה גסה *U'vehemah gasah* means large. Yeah, so that's very generic.
You wonder if there was not another פסוק *pasuk* other than בהמה
רבה *behemah rabah*, but presumably they would have quoted it. Anyway, that's
where they get their debate. So he says, they say בהמה *behemah*
can mean multiple and he says it only means singular. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this. וטעמא דרבי שמעון משום
בהמה הוא hu, *V'taama d'Rabbi Shimon mishum behemah hu*? Is that his
reasoning? Because בהמה *behemah* is singular? והא טעמא דרבי שמעון משום הוא
hu *V'ha taama d'Rabbi Shimon mishum hu*. But in the משנה Mishna.
*Mishnah* his reason is from the word הוא hu *hu* in the
singular. מה הוא hu מיוחד אף תמורתו מיוחדת *Mah hu meyuchad af
tmurato meyuchadet*. So how do you, so which is he getting it
from? The word בהמה *behemah* or the word from הוא *hu*? So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* here actually gives quite a fascinating answer. מעיקרא
אמר להו רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon מן והיה הוא ותמורתו *Me'ikara amar
lehu Rabbi Shimon min v'hayah hu u'tmurato*. He said, yeah, הוא ותמורתו
*hu u'tmurato*, it's all singular. וכי חזא דדרשי רבנן מבהמה בבהמה *V'chi
chaza d'darshi rabanan m'behemah b'vehemah*, he saw they were latching on to
the word בהמה *behemah* trying to interpret that the word בהמה *behemah*
can mean singular or multiple. אמר להו איהו *Amar lehu ihu*, so
he said, you want to talk about בהמה *behemah*? Let's talk about
בהמה *behemah*. מהתם נמי מצינא למימר לטעמיה דידי *Mehatam nami matzina l'meimar
l'taameih didi*. I can also say my position from the word בהמה
*behemah*. בהמה *Behemah* is also singular. So he said, they they tried
to get out of my הוא *hu* argument by saying בהמה *behemah*
means multiple, I'll fight them on their own turf and I'll tell
them בהמה *behemah* also means singular. All right, that was very nice.
Now, מן הבהמה הטהורה *Min habehemah hatehorah* is used often generically. Yeah.
מן הבהמה הטהורה *Min habehemah hatehorah*.
Right.
Right. Okay, so now the גמרא *Gemara* says like this. אמר ריש
לקיש Reish Lakish מודה רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon, *Amar Reish Lakish modeh
Rabbi Shimon*. Now that that was the דרשות drashas, *drashot*. Now we're
going to get to the content. Okay, so רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon,
*Rabbi Shimon* says you can't do two for one. So he's going
to be the interesting position to explore. What exactly are the limits
of his position? So מודה רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon. שממירין וחוזרין וממירין
*Modeh Rabbi Shimon shememirin v'chozrin u'memirin*. You can't do one for two.
I can't take this one animal that's קרבן korban *korban* and transfer
it to two, but I can transfer two times. I have my
one קרבן korban, *korban* and I say this goes on this. Boom,
תמורה tmura *tmurah*, I get lashes. Get out of here. Take a
new animal. This goes on this. Boom, I get lashes. Okay, so
it was one to two, but they were sequential. It was two
cases of one to one. That you can do. מאי טעמא *Mai
taama*? What's the reason? קדושה kedusha ראשונה דהקדש להיכן הלכה halacha *Kedushah
rishonah d'hekdesh l'heichan halchah*? Why shouldn't it be? The first, the origin
of the קדושה kedusha *kedushah*, the animal I sanctified, that was never
impacted even though I did תמורה tmura, *tmurah*. Since the original קדושה
kedusha *kedushah* remains, I can do it from this animal multiple times
as long as each time is a one for one. ורבי יוחנן
אמר לא *V'Rabbi Yochanan amar lo*. No. ורבי יוחנן אמר לא כשם
שאין ממירין שנים באחד כך אין ממירין וחוזרין וממירין *V'Rabbi Yochanan amar
lo keshem she'ein memirin shnayim b'echad kach ein memirin v'chozrin u'memirin*. The
same way you can't do one, you know, two for one, you
can't do the same thing twice. ואיכא חכמים Chachamim *V'ika chachamim*?
No, no, no. All according to, no, no, no, this is just
within רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon*. So his limit is not just you
can't do an unequal exchange, his real point is is that you
can only do a תמורה tmura. *tmurah* once, okay, for once and
for one animal. And therefore if you've done it once, you won't
be able to do it a second time. תניא כוותיה דרבי יוחנן
ותניא כוותיה דריש לקיש *Tanya k'vateih d'Rabbi Yochanan v'tanya k'vateih d'Reish Lakish*.
We taught a ברייתא *braita* like each one. תניא כוותיה דרבי יוחנן
*Tanya k'vateih d'Rabbi Yochanan*. כשם שאין ממירין אחד בשנים *Keshem she'ein memirin
echad b'shnayim*, the same way you can't take one קרבן korban *korban*
and do two animals instead, כך אין ממירין וחוזרין וממירין *kach ein
memirin v'chozrin u'memirin*. You can't do one קרבן korban. *korban* and do
it twice. What? This is all according to רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon*.
תניא כוותיה דריש לקיש *Tanya k'vateih d'Reish Lakish* what says כשם *keshem*.
So כשם *keshem* is working within רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon*. תניא כוותיה
דריש לקיש *Tanya k'vateih d'Reish Lakish*. יכול כשם שאמר רבי שמעון אין
ממירין שנים באחד כך אין ממירין וחוזרין וממירין *Yachol keshem she'amar Rabbi
Shimon ein memirin shnayim b'echad kach ein memirin v'chozrin u'memirin*? So a
ברייתא *braita*, this ברייתא *braita* says the same, maybe I would think
that the same way רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* says you can't do
two for one, you can't therefore do two animals even sequentially? תלמוד
לומר והיה הוא ותמורתו *Talmud lomar v'hayah hu u'tmurato*. It and its
תמורה tmura, *tmurah*. אפילו מאה במאה *Afilu meah b'meah*, even if you
do it a hundred times as long as you're doing them sequentially.
I don't exactly get how it gets from the פסוק *pasuk*, but
regardless, we have one position that according to רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon*
you can do it multiple times as long as each time is
one for one. which is ריש לקיש'ס makes more sense I would
think, but רבי יוחנן'ס Rabbi Yochanan's position which is no, there's a
limit of one exchange for one animal. Now we're going to ask
now that we've explored an interesting possibility within רבי שמעון, we're going
to try to explore again every time somebody says you can't do
it, if you say you can do it then it's not so
interesting because then fine there's nothing to explore. But if you say
you can't do it then you want to know what are the
limits of that, like how much are you limited. So first רבי
שמעון said you can't do two for one, then רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan said oh you can't even do you know one for one
multiple times. So that's
a further limit, a further you know, so now we're going to
say within רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan you can't do one for one
multiple times, what cases would be included in that?
You could have asked even according to the חכמים Chachamim who say
you can do one for two hundred or meaning you can only
do it once but then
meaning who says no there's no logic for it. Only with רבי
שמעון who introduces a limit is there a question to ask is
doing multiple times the same as doing two for one. With the
חכמים Chachamim there's no reason to think they would have any limit,
right? And the logic of ריש לקיש is
compelling, קדושה ראשונה להיכן הלכה. kedusha rishona leheichan halcha. So that obviously
there's no reason to assume unless you're already introducing certain limits and
then the question is maybe this is an extension of those limits.
We just discussed making a chain like the
no that we will discuss and that the basic הלכה halacha is
אין תמורה עושה תמורה. ein tmura osa tmura. When the derivative תמורה
tmura. is not קדושה kedusha. is not powerful enough to make another
one. So that we're not discussing now and that even the חכמים
agree to, that's not based on this debate. Okay, but here the
point is קדושה ראשונה להיכן הלכה, kedusha rishona leheichan halcha, we're all
focusing on the original animal. Okay, בעי רבי אבין, ba'ei Rabbi Avin,
so רבי אבין Rabbi Avin asks, לדברי האומר אין מימר וחוזר ומימר,
ledivrei ha'omer ein mimir vechozer u'mimir, now within רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
who says you can't do it multiple times from the same animal
who's doing within רבי שמעון,
הפריש אשם להתכפר בו והימר בו. hifrish asham lehitkaper bo veheimir bo.
So now we're going to have a little complicated case. He separated
out an אשם, asham, okay the reason we're going to talk about
an אשם asham is you might remember that the הלכה halacha of
an אשם asham is that if you lose this animal and you
bring another קרבן korban. for your אשם asham instead and then you
find the original one, so if it were a חטאת chatas the
הלכה halacha of חטאת שנתכפרו בעליה באחר chatas shenitkapru ba'aleha be'acher is
you have to let it die. But אשם שנתכפרו בעליה באחר asham
shenitkapru ba'aleha be'acher the הלכה halacha? is that it basically becomes an
עולה. olah. It becomes an עולה. olah. So what we're going to
be dealing with, the reason therefore we're dealing with the אשם asham
case is because if the קדושה kedusha transfers, the identity of the
קדושה kedusha transfers, is it considered the same animal? Right? The same
קדושה. kedusha, So according to the idea you cannot take from the
same animal and do more than one תמורה, tmura which is רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan within רבי שמעון, let's say the קדושה kedusha. of
the first animal changes, it switched from אשם asham to עולה. olah.
Now maybe it's like a new thing and now maybe I can
do another תמורה. tmura Okay so that's why we're doing this case.
We're going to make it it's still בהמה, you
learn it from the פסוק. Okay interesting. But now we're going to
do but still a new identity. But now we're going to make
it even more complicated than that. That's one way it might be
new is that the קדושה kedusha switched from אשם asham to עולה.
olah. Okay so what happened is is that I take I took
this אשם asham and I did תמורה, tmura I used it once.
We have to say I used it once because the question is
going to be can I use it a second time. Now הומם,
hiumam, now it got a blemish, this original one. וחיללו על אחר,
vechilelo al acher, I transferred it to another animal. Okay I did
what should I do with an animal with a blemish and we
discussed before how come that is not תמורה. tmura ונתכפר באשם אחר,
venitkaper be'asham acher,
now I've got animal number two that's going to be my אשם
asham and I lost animal number two. No wait what's the case?
I have there's my original אשם, asham, okay I did תמורה tmura
once, so the question is going to be can I do תמורה
temurah again with this. Now this got a blemish, so I replaced
it with this. This is now the one that has the קדושה,
kedusha it's derivative from this קדושה. kedusha
Now this one got lost and I brought another קרבן, then I
found this one again. So the purpose of something getting lost and
being brought another and finding it again means that this אשם asham
now becomes what? What did I tell you it becomes? An עולה.
olah. When I did when it got lost and I brought something
instead and then I found it, the קדושה kedusha... transfers from אשם
asham to עולה. olah. So this is now different from the original
one in two ways, right? It's not the same animal as the
original one, it's derivative of the קדושה kedusha. but it's not the
same animal
and it's not no longer קדושת אשם, kedushas asham, it's קדושת עולה.
kedushas olah. So there are two things that make this different. Can
I now do תמורה temurah with this? Is it the same it
is that only one תמורה temurah for one animal from the original
animal and this is not the original in two ways. It's a
different physical animal and although the קדושה kedusha was derivative it also
transformed into that.
Wait is there one of the ways you couldn't do it?
Well that's what the גמרא is going to ask. Why did you
jump to this complicated case, ask first the individual components. Okay good.
So let's take a look. ונתכפר באשם אחר, venitkaper be'asham acher, used
another one, וניתק לעולה, venitak le'olah, and now this became the עולה.
olah. מהו שימיר בו, mahu sheyamir bo, can I now do תמורה
temurah with this? אמר אביי, amar Abaye, מאי קמיבעיא ליה, mai ka
miba'ei lei, what's your question? אי ב' גופין וקדושה אחת, ibei gufin
vekedusha achas, if your question was a different animal although derivative קדושה...
kedusha,
Don't give the fancy case that you lost it and found another.
Just say this original one got a blemish, I transferred it to
this, so this is now a physically different animal but it's derivative
קדושה. kedusha Is it considered the same or is it considered different?
Right? After without being so fancy, just ask it's a new animal,
maybe that should make it different. Okay, so ask that case. Okay,
תיבעי ליה Tibaya lei אי בבית קדושה דגוף אחד ee beis kedusha
d'guf echad if your question more is when it transforms from אשם
asham קדושה kedusha to עולה olah קדושה, kedusha maybe that brings a
change of identity, תיבעי ליה בלאו הכי. tibaya lei b'lav hachi. So
don't talk about this new thing, just talk about the original thing,
got lost, brought another, and then the קדושה kedusha transfers from אשם
asham to עולה. olah. So basically why are you making such a
hybrid case that has two things different? Ask about each one individually.
What if it's the same קדושה kedusha but a different animal because
you got a blemish and you transferred it? What if it's the
same animal but a different קדושה kedusha because it transferred from אשם
asham to עולה? olah? So why not just ask each one individually?
So the גמרא says
ורב אבין, V'Rav Avin, what was רב אבין Rav Avin thinking? So
רב אבין Rav Avin חדא מגו חדא קמיבעיא ליה. chada migu chada
ka mibaya lei. He's asking one based on the other. ואם תמצא
לומר V'im timtza lomar שתי גופים וקדושה אחת לא, shnei gufim u'kedusha
achas lo, meaning what he asked is more complicated. He was saying
look, even if you tell me some of the individual cases are
considered the same, what if you have it different in two ways?
So he was implicitly asking what's the story if it's only different
in one way, and even if you say that's not enough of
a difference, what if it's different in two ways? Okay, so that
is exactly essentially what he was asking. אם תמצא לומר שתי גופים
וקדושה אחת לא, Im timtza lomar shnei gufim u'kedusha achas lo, if
you say שתי גופים וקדושה אחת לא shnei gufim u'kedusha achas lo
when it's just a new animal but it's the same
קדושה kedusha that's been derived, משום דבהא קדושה איתמר בה, mishum d'beha
kedusha itamer ba, this is a very, I got stuck on this
word. איתמר Itmar means to say. Okay, but the word is here
איתמר בה. itamer ba. You did a תמורה Temurah on it, not
איתמר. itmar. If you look at the little aleph in the שיטה
מקובצת, Shita Mekubetzes, it gives you the pronunciation איתמר
בה. itamer ba. You did a תמורה temurah on it, not איתמר.
itmar. Okay, so if you say that if it's just a new
animal but it's the same קדושה kedusha that's been derived and that
you can't do it twice because you already did a תמורה tmura
act on this קדושה kedusha, once, not on this animal but on
this קדושה kedusha, because the second animal takes the place of the
first, so חדא זימנא chada zimna because you already did it once,
שתי גופים ושתי קדושות מהו? shnei gufim u'shnei kedushos mahu? Let's say
you had both things combined. Not only was it a physically different
animal, but the קדושה kedusha transformed from אשם asham to עולה. olah.
And the answer is תיקו. teiku. Okay, so you're right, it's a
complicated case, it's a complicated case, but it basically means I want
to ask all of them. What if you have only one difference,
a physically different animal or a different קדושה, kedusha same animal, and
even if you say those things are not by themselves enough to
say that you're allowed that you're able to do תמורה tmura second
time, let's say it was different in both ways. And the גמרא
says תיקו. teiku.
In all these cases?
Yeah, we don't know exactly, we don't know the answer to any
of those. לישנא אחרינא, Lishna achrina, now you know when you get
to a לישנא אחרינא lishna achrina we're going to do the same
thing but basically just different words. So we get a lot of
חזרה chazara in תמורה tmura. because there's a lot of לישנא אחרינא.
lishna achrina. לישנא אחרינא, Lishna achrina, בעי רב אבין מרבי יוחנן. ba'ei
Rav Avin mei'Rabbi Yochanan. רב אבין Rav Avin asked לרבי יוחנן, l'Rabbi
Yochanan, excuse me, דאמר אין למדים חוזרים וממירים, d'amar ein l'medim chozrim
u'memirim, you can't do it more than once with the same animal,
who's saying that within רבי שמעון. הפריש אשם להתכפר בו, Hifrish asham
l'hiskafer bo,
so you separated out an אשם, asham, והמיר בו, v'hemir bo, you
did תמורה tmura, once, והומם וחיללו על אחר, v'humam v'chilalo al achair,
and now you transferred it to another one, מהו שיחזור וימיר? mahu
sheyachzor v'yamir? So now in this version he didn't ask the complicated
case, he asked the simple case, that you now have a second
animal that has transferred the קדושה, kedusha, and so it's derivative קדושה
kedusha, but it's a second animal. Same קדושה kedusha but a different
animal. What's the הלכה? halacha נתכפר באשם אחר וניתק זה לעולה מהו
שיחזור וימיר? Niskafer b'asham achair v'nitak zeh l'olah mahu sheyachzor v'yamir? Or
what about the other case? Let's say there's no second animal but
this animal transformed from an אשם asham into an עולה. olah. What's
the story? So according to this version, rather than asking the hybrid
case, he asked the two individual components. What's the story if it's
a new animal but the same קדושה, kedusha, the first one had
a blemish? What's the story if it's the same animal but a
new קדושה, kedusha? it was an אשם asham that became an עולה?
olah? Okay, and he asked what's the story with each individual component.
אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, now אביי Abaye said, האי קמיבעיא ליה, hai
ka mibaya lei, which one is his real question? Somehow אביי Abaye
thought, it's not clear why, that he had to have that one
of them was more obvious than the other of those two scenarios.
Which one is really bothering him? קדושה אחרת באותו גוף לא מיבעיא
ליה. Kedusha acheres b'oso guf lo mibaya lei. If what's really bothering
him is the case of what he really thinks might be different
is when it is a new קדושה kedusha, in the same body,
meaning it transfers from an אשם asham to an עולה, olah, so
לא מיבעיא ליה הומם וחיללו lo mibaya lei humam v'chilalo don't ask
the case of transferring it to another animal באחר. b'achair. אי גוף
אחד באותה קדושה, Ee guf echad b'osah kedusha, if the case that's
really concerning him is what happens if it is, now it's funny,
in this version the word גוף אחד guf echad really means, I
don't know why, it means another body. It really means like גוף
אחר. guf achair. It's quite confusing, I know, but it says many
many times and every time it's גוף אחד. guf echad. Okay. But
for whatever reason גוף אחד guf echad in this version means a
different physical body. Okay, if it's a different body באותה קדושה b'oso
kedusha and it's the same קדושה, kedusha, that's what bothers him. That's
his real question. What happens if it's a different animal but the
same קדושה? kedusha לא ניבעי נתכפר באשם אחר, lo niba'i niskaper b'asham
acher, don't ask the case of transferring from an אשם asham to
an עולה. olah. So for Rebbe Abba, so why did Rebbe Abba
ask both? חדא מיגו חדא קמיבעיא ליה chada migo chada k'miba'i lei
because he wasn't certain about both of them. Maybe one he was
a little more clear to him that that was should maybe, you
know, but neither of them was he totally certain about. And here's
what he was saying. הוא מחילול אחר מהו שיחזור וימיר, hu m'chilul
acher mah sheyachzor v'yemer, number one, if you transferred the קדושה, kedusha.
can you do a תמורה tmura, now with the second animal? מי
אמרינן באשם ראשון הוא דאין חוזר ומימר, mi amrinan b'asham rishon hu
d'ein chozer v'meimer, maybe only the first one you can't because that's
the same animal. But בגוף אחד, b'guf echad, again, funny word, in
one body meaning in a different body, אף על גב דקדיש אותה
קדושה, af al gav d'kadesh oso kedusha, although it has the same
קדושה, kedusha. חוזר ומימר, chozer v'meimer, maybe you should be able to
do it. So his first question was, can you do it if
it's the same קדושה kedusha. in a different body? But that was
a little more obvious to him that that shouldn't work because fundamentally
it was the same קדושה. kedusha, או דילמא, o dilma, or did
he say, כל באותה קדושה אין חוזר ומימר. kol b'oso kedusha ein
chozer v'meimer. So at the end of the day, it's the same
קדושה. kedusha. So even though he was asking that question, that was
his first question, you know, that was like his first offer. That
he understood was probably most likely not going to work because it
was fundamentally the same קדושה. kedusha And then he asked his second
one. ואם תמצא לומר הדין גוף אחד, v'im timtza lomar hadain guf
echad, this again, new body, it says so funny אחד, this new
animal, כיון דבאותה קדושה קדוש, keivan d'b'oso kedusha kadosh, since it has
the same קדושה, kedusha, אין חוזר ומימר, ein chozer v'meimer, you can't
do it again. So if that's true, you say the first one,
ah, it's all the same קדושה. kedusha. Let me ask my second
question, which is a more serious one. אלא נתכפר באשם אחר, ela
niskaper b'asham acher, let's say you had, you brought another קרבן and
therefore וניתק זה ראשון לעולה, v'nitak zeh rishon l'olah, the קדושה kedusha,
transformed from אשם asham to עולה, olah, so it's a really different
קדושה, kedusha
that I really, that's a serious possibility. מהו שיחזור וימיר בו, mah
sheyachzor v'yemer bo, can you do תמורה tmura with that? מי אמרינן,
mi amrinan, do we say, כי אין מימר וחוזר ומימר הני מילי
באותו גוף באותה קדושה, ki ein meimer v'chozer v'meimer hani mili b'oso
guf b'oso kedusha, when can you not do it twice? That's when
it's the same body, same קדושה. kedusha אבל אותו גוף בקדושה אחרת,
aval oso guf b'kedusha acheres, although it's the same physical body, it's
a different קדושה, kedusha, it transferred from אשם asham to עולה, olah,
חוזר ומימר, chozer v'meimer, that you can do תמורה. tmurah, או דילמא,
o dilma, or do we say, אף על קדושה אחרת, af al
kedusha acheres, even when the קדושה kedusha transformed, כיון דאותו גוף הוא,
keivan d'oso guf hu, since it's at least the same body, אין
חוזר ומימר, ein chozer v'meimer, you cannot do it, תיקו. teiku. So
again, one minute, so again we had the same series of questions,
although it was a little bit easier because it asked the two
components separately. And it seemed to, and it seemed to say that
well, it was the, if it's the same קדושה kedusha? derivative, it's
more obvious it's still a problem, it's still limited, but a transformed
קדושה, kedusha. that's a more serious question. But at least this was
an easier version because it asked those issues separately and it left
with a תיקו, teiku, which by the way raises an interesting question,
which is according to this second version, if it was a hybrid
of the two, maybe that would have been obvious that it actually
would work, right? Because it never, it never got around to asking
the most complex question, right, when it's a transformed קדושה kedusha and
a different animal. That was only asked in the first version.
But again, in some ways it's a תיקו, teiku, it's pretty clear
that Rebbe Shimon said הוא, you know, it. It doesn't mean it's
like a, you know, like a...
All right, so the question is how much of a literalist are
you? הוא because it's the same קדושה?
kedusha, You'd have to be very literal, that's the whole point.
I mean, תמורה, tmurah. הוא the physical object, הוא the same קדושה.
kedusha. הוא הבהמה. hu hab'heima. All right, I don't know what to
say, Michael. They thought it was a question. Let's keep on going.
Yes.
So then they ask, why did you ask two separate questions? Why
not ask one big question?
Right, that's also fun. But the second version seems to be like,
you know, normally ask one question at a time. Don't just dump
down all your questions. So the point is it has to understand
that they are somehow, you know, sequential or structured questions. Like, I
understand this one you'll probably give me this answer, but how about
this one?
Okay, but anyway, right, Socratic method as opposed to real practical, down-to-earth
system.
Right.
Okay, did you say anything about what I was saying? Because I
mean, to me it seems like Rebbe Shimon is very literal.
Michael, you get very concerned about דרשות, most, okay, but let's keep
on going. אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי, amar Rebbe Yehoshua ben Levi,
הקדש ראשון מוסיף חומש והקדש שני מוסיף חומש. hektesh rishon mosif chomesh
v'hektesh sheni mosif chomesh. Only the first sanctity you add a fifth,
not the second sanctity. What does this mean? The הלכה is is
that if you redeem something that's been sanctified, איש כי יקדיש את
ביתו קדש לה', ish ki yakdish es beiso kodesh l'Hashem, and if
you redeem it, that you add a fifth. Now, what happens if
I sanctified this thing and then the way I redeemed it by
adding a fifth was I transferred it onto something else? Okay, so
I sanctified my house and then I transferred the קדושה kedusha. onto
my onto my camera. Okay, so so therefore that was at least
a fifth more. Now I want to redeem my camera. Do I
have to go up to a, I don't know, Lexus? Do I
have to add a fifth on that or since that is already
derivative קדושה, kedusha I don't add a fifth to the derivative קדושה.
kedusha. I only add a fifth to the original קדושה. kedusha So
that's what he said. You're talking about תמורה, tmurah, not like... Right,
although תמורה tmurah. you could do again, not... As a תמורה, if
it gets a blemish and you do it as a פדיון, pidyon,
you're allowed to do it. That's what we said at the beginning,
but that's the irony. If the thing gets a blemish, you do
redeem it, you just have to be careful that the way you
redeem it doesn't isn't defined as an act of exchange, an act
of תמורה. Okay. So אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי, Amar Rabbi Yehoshua
ben Levi, הקדש ראשון מוסיף חומש, hekdesh rishon mosif chomesh, the first
one you add a fifth, ואין הקדש שני מוסיף חומש, ve'ein hekdesh
sheni mosif chomesh, not the second one. That's derivative. אמר רב פפא,
Amar Rav Pappa, מאי טעמא דרבי יהושע בן לוי? mai ta'ama deRabbi
Yehoshua ben Levi? What's his reasoning? אמר קרא, Amar kra, ואם המקדיש
יגאל את ביתו, ve'im hamakdish yigal et beito, if the sanctifier redeems
his house, that was a case in the Torah that you sanctified
your house, ויסף חמישית כסף ערכך עליו וקם לו. veyasaf chamishit kesef
erkecha alav vekam lo. You add a fifth. So it says המקדיש.
hamakdish. מקדיש ולא מטפיס. makdish velo matpis.
The one that sanctifies, not the one here they're saying מטפיס, matpis,
which basically means grabs onto an existing sanctity. So when I when
I
had my Ford and then I redeemed it and transferred it to
my Camry, I was מטפיס matpis my Camry with the קדושה kedusha
of the Ford. I did not give it a new קדושה. kedusha.
I wasn't מקדיש. makdish. I didn't directly מקדיש makdish it. I took
the existing קדושה from the Ford and transferred it to the Camry.
That was מטפיס. matpis. So the Torah says when you're המקדיש, hamakdish,
it's a context of the original קדושה you installed, that's when you
add a fifth, not when it was some transferred קדושה. בעי רבי
אבין: Ba'ei Rabbi Avin: הפריש אשם להתכפר בו. hifrish asham lehitkaper bo.
You thought we were out of that. Okay. Now that there's a
difference between the original and the derivative, guess what we're going to
ask? Our famous our you know our our lovely אשם asham case.
Is that going to be defined as the original or the derivative?
Right? You see where this is heading? I hope you do. Okay.
הפריש אשם להתכפר בו. hifrish asham lehitkaper bo. You separated to now
we're going to understand that this statement here is not just about
בדק הבית, bedek habayit, it's even about קרבנות. korbanot. Okay. And when
you're now redeeming them, before we were talking about תמורה, which was
forbidden, but you could also talk about redeeming when it gets a
blemish, which is permissible. So when you're going to redeem, are you
redeeming the original or is it going to be considered to be
the derivative? Let's take a look. הפריש אשם להתכפר בו. hifrish asham
lehitkaper bo. You set aside an אשם. asham. והומם. vehumam. It got
a blemish. והוסיף עליו חומש. vehosif alav chomesh. Notice here we're not
talking about תמורה. You're doing a legitimate redemption. You added a fifth.
וחיללו. vechilalo. And now you transferred it to another animal. Okay. וחיללו
על חבירו. vechilalo al chaveiro. ונתכפר. venitkaper.
Now, ונתכפר באשם אחר וניתק זה לעולה. venitkaper be'asham acher venittak zeh
le'olah. Now the second אשם asham now went, you know, went ahead,
got lost, whatever, now it transferred into an...
Does he add on a fifth when it gets a מום? mum?
When you're when you're...? Yes. That's what he's supposed to. Yeah. So
so it's not only when you just want to like, you know,
from בדק הבית bedek habayit you just want to get rid of
it and not get rid of it, but it's not like I'm
redeeming my house at all. So as a punishment for redeeming, they
add on a fifth. It's even if it has a מום mum
and you can't use it, it's a קרבן. You add a fifth
when you...? Right. But only me, right? But if you do it...?
Correct, but I'm not normally able to redeem your קרבן. Okay, it's
a little different than בדק הבית bedek habayit where anybody can come
and redeem. Okay. So מהו שיוסיף עליו חומש? mahu sheyosif alav chomesh?
Now I want to now I head go ahead and redeem this.
Do I add a fifth or not? Now the obvious question here,
let me just check I just need to check רש״י Rashi for
one second. Hold on a
minute.
One
minute. One minute.
Let me look at
the משנה.
Ah, okay, fine. Okay, I just wanted to check this. Okay, so
meaning because here the obvious question is going to be, okay, so
here the point is, so what did you do? Once again, you
transferred it to the second animal and this animal is now different
in two ways. This animal number one is a physically different animal.
Number two, it's transferred from an אשם asham to an עולה. olah.
And because of those things, we want to know, is this going
to be considered the original or is this going to be considered
the new one? And if it's the new one, then you would
add a fifth, right? So if it were a normal case, right?
A normal case is I added a fifth, I transferred it. So
that seems to be the case that we said. So now if
I wanted to redeem the second one, I wouldn't add another fifth,
right? Because it's derivative, it's only the original one. But this thing
now is actually different, it might be new because not only is
it a physically another object, but also it transferred from an אשם
asham to an עולה. olah. So maybe because of those things... It's
considered to be completely new, and now if I redeem this one,
I will add a fifth. Okay, so that is the question. So
let's take a look. It says like
this: אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, said Abaye. Okay. We'll have to find
out the answer to this.